[Música]
Probando. Uno, dos, uno, dos.
Uno, dos, tres, cuatro.
El rápido zorro café salta sobre el perro perezoso.
Este es el podcast de React. Soy Chantastic.
Hoy vamos a volver atrás. Muy, muy atrás. De regreso a los inicios
de React. Mirando 10 años atrás,
pareciería que React siempre estuvo destinado a triunfar.
Que un framework hecho por Facebook era demasiado grande para fallar.
Pero esta no es ese tipo de historia.
De hecho, hubieron muchas ocasiones en la historia de Reacts
donde parecia que no iba a tener éxito en lo absoluto.
Entonces, ¿qué pasó?
¿Como es que React paso en 10 años de verse muerto al llegar
How did react go, in 10 years, from looking
a ser el framework de front-end de
Javascript dominante que es ahora?
Todo empieza en el 2011 en Facebook. jQuery y Backbone
dominaban el front-end en JavaScript
pero herramientas pragmáticas como Ember, Angular y
Knockout entraron en escena. En el mundo exterior
"Gangnam Style" recién se había subido a YouTube,
"Call Me Maybe" estaba en la cima de las listas de música
y el meme más reciente era el de "La Novia Psicópata"
En tiempo del Internet,
básicamente una eternidad. Así que ponte el cinturón de seguridad,
desconéctate de todo, y habilita el modo de "no molestar",
porque está es la historia de algo que tenía pocas posibilidad de ganar.
[Música]
Veo que esta cámara tiene una luz roja,
pero está otra no lo tiene.
[Música]
Solo sujétalo con esto.
Probando uno dos, probando.
Testing one two, testing.
[Música]
[La computadora se enciende]
Cuando obtuve la oferta para trabajar en Facebook,
le conté a mi mamá. Estaba muy emocionado.
La película "La Red Social" se había estrenado,
y ella la había visto recientemente.
Ella constantemente me desanimaba de aceptar
porque pensaba que Mark Zuckerberg
no parecía una buena persona. Durante el tiempo
en el que trabajé en Facebook,
no creo que vuelva a existir algo similar nunca más.
No era algo que que hubiese experimentado antes.
Solo unos meses antes de unirme, Kanye West visitó
las oficinas de Facebook,
se subió a una mesa de la cafetería
y rapeó algunas rimas
y estaba trabajando con esta persona que recién se había
graduado de la Universidad,
y yo estaba tratando de explicarle que había trabajado
en estos trabajos de mierda en software. Para ese entonces,
ya habían sido 10 o 15 años, y nada como esto había pasado antes,
no en la ingeniería de software.
"♪ Eres mi estrés, eres mi masajista ♪"
En aquel tiempo, JavaScript pasaba por un poco
de crisis existencial,
acerca de si ser más como un lenguagje de programación real,
o un lenguaje de programación de juguete.
Había mucha agitación. jQuery era popular,
MooTools era popular,
y había tantas opciones diferentes en guerra
tratando de llegar a la mente del público.
Y había muchas similitudes entre ellos, pero cada
una tenía sútiles diferencias
one had its kind of bespoke differences and
y ninguna era realmente fantástica para construir
interfaces de usuario y aplicaciones complejas.
Había esta tendencia más hacia aplicaciones sofisticadas.
towards more sophisticated applications that
que hacían más cosas, y en Facebook todavía
priorizabamos la tecnología para hacer render en el server,
y una de las cosas por las cuales
estuvimos en contra por un largo tiempo
fue simplemente incrementar el tamaño de los paquetes de JavaScript,
así que conforme moviamos más y más cosas al lado del cliente,
el cliente se volvía más y más lento, así que en realidad
nos cambiamos hacia el render del lado del servidor
y hacia pequeñas pedazos de JavaScript por un tiempo.
Y había esta sensación de que
sabíamos que lo que estábamos haciendo para
el desarrollo en el lado del cliente no estaba funcionando
development wasn't working but also that server
pero también lo que teníamos en el lado del servidor no nos iba a llevar
a ningún lado.
So I think that was the kind of environment
Creo que ese fue el tipo de ambiente del nació
salió React.
[Música]
Cuando me uní a Facebook en el 2010, había colaborado mucho
en código libre, particularmente
en el mundo de JavaScript. Era un colaborador en la herramienta
Dojo.js en aquel entonces
el cual es uno de los abuelos del movimiento de JavaScript, junto
a los prototipos y jQuery.
Pasé mis primeros dos años en Facebook en el equipo de desarrollo móvil.
Empezamos con una gran determinación
the mobile team. We had started off a big
para competir con Apple y Google, y pensamos
que nuestra mayor oportunidad de éxito
como compañía era ir directamente hacia la web, y
abogar para construir el ecosistema de HTML5.
Así que, como parte de eso, yo y otros dos ingenieros
llamados Vladimir Kolesnikov y Will Bailey
construimos un framework llamado Bolt.js (Tornillo.js)
Lo llamamos así porque
justo "atornillábamos" muchas cosas que cada uno nos interesaba.
"Bolt" era básicamente más o menos la implementación de Facebook
de un modelo vista-controlador (MVC) para el lado del cliente.
Creo que era una versión bastante buena, tal vez una mejor versión
a pretty good version, maybe a better version,
de cosas como Backbone y algunos otros frameworks que existían
en aquellos tiempos.
Pero nació desde unas limitaciones muy específicas de Facebook.
Es el corazón de tu experiencia en Facebook.
Lo re-pensamos completamente desde las raíces.
Habíamos trabajado en el durante todo el año,
y lo llamábamos "Timeline". Facebook era uno de los primeros
grandes productos que era realmente una experiencia más que nada.
No estás tratando de comprar comida u obtener boletos,
o algo así en Facebook.
Lo que realmente quieres es entretenimiento.
Y por ello sabes que la interfaz de usuario
necesita ser interesante. Bolt no solo era
una caja de herramientas,
realmente era un framework para desarrollo de aplicaciones.
Algo diseñado y hecho para construir
aplicaciones complejas y altamente interactivas, y estaba siendo
usando para construir productos realmente complejos
en Facebook. Al final terminamos prácticamente recreando
la mayor parte de Facebook:
toda la variedad de aplicaciones: timeline, chat, la sección
de noticias. Teníamos toda una aplicación de fotos
que construimos, y obviamente el equipo tenía que expandirlo.
Así que en algún punto pensé
que probablemente teníamos alrededor de 25 ingenieros trabajando
en todo esto, entre los que construían Bolt y
y los que creaban aplicacions usando Bolt, y eso solamente
contando al equipo de aplicaciones móviles.
Bolt nunca fue el problema, fue la arquitectura lo que terminó
por derrotarnos. El producto por sí mismo
se volvió más complejo, y entre más añadíamos ingenieros al equipo,
no nos topamos con la pared, pero si comenzó a ser
to the team, we didn't hit a wall but it started
muy, muy díficil hacer cambios.
Fue justo por aquellas fechas
que Jordan estaba en el equipo de anuncios, y el se comenzó
a preguntar si había una mejor forma.
Jordan es una figura enigmática. El el un poco privado,
así que no hay mucho que sepa de el.
Jordan y yo no eramos el centro de atención.
Especialmente Jordan evitaba ser el centro de atención
desde los primeros días.
Jordan era un ingeniero de producto por aquel entonces,
trabajando en anuncios, y los anuncios eran una de las partes
de interfaz de usuario más complicadas de todo Facebook.
Como equipo, se topaban constantemente
On the as team they were hitting much
con los límmites de lo que se podía lograr sin React,
hablando de complejidad.
Y solo la habilidad de los desarrolladores para mantener en su mente
y entender un poco de código que alguien más había hecho
mientras miran el monitor y decir: "ok, entonces este código
hace esto y necesito saber porqué".
Jordan tenía muchas ideas muy interesantes acerca de como
podríamos tomar lo que se había hecho en Bolt y hacerlo más
funcional y fácil de escalar
junto con la habilidad de las personas de
entender aplicaciones grandes
Así que teníamos muchas conversaciones, y el
iba y venía con nosotros con varias ideas
acerca de como cambiarlo. Creo que uno de los nombres originales
para React era FBolt,
que significaba Functional Bolt.
Jordan vio que había una oportunidad de resolver algunas de
las partes más complicadas en Bolt
de una forma más sencilla. Así que lo que Jordan decidió
hacer, o al menos la historia que me contó
fue: "Oye, no sería más sencillo si cada vez que algo cambiara
en la app: el estado de la API, el usuario escribió algo...
solamente destruyéramos toda la UI y
volvieramos a recrear todo?"
Lo que el resto de los frameworks hacía entonces se llamaba
"enlace de datos bi-direccional"
y esto no era eso. Era alg así como:
olvídate del enlace de datos
no vamos a hacer eso en lo absoluto.
Cada vez que algo cambie vamos a repintar todo
pero hay un gran asterico que dice "en realidad no vamos
a repintar todo, vamos a repintar lo menos posible"
pero conceptualmente no vamos a manejar estas relaciones
entre vistas y modelos
Honestamente pensé que era una una locura.
Por aquel entonces estaba muy convencido en la idea de los
frameworks en general,
y pensé que algo así no iba a funcionar. Para algunas personas,
parecía magia. Estaba muy lejos
de la idea que todos tenían acerca de como funcionaban y
como deberían funcionar las cosas. Tomó mucho para convencerlos.
[Música]
He trabajado en Facebook por 10 años hasta ahora.
Y conocí a esta persona llamada Jordan Walke.
Algunas personas me decían que el tenía un proyecto interesante
acerca de JavaScript, y que tal vez me interesaría.
Así que tuve una junta con él y una de las cosas
que me preguntó al inicio de la reunión fue
"qué es lo más difícil de hacer en el Front End hasta ahora?"
Y bueno,
yo llevaba 6 meses que me había graduado de la escuela.
Respondí: "no sé". Y lo que me dijo fue:
"las actualizaciones". Tienees que encontrar el nodo del DOM
que va a cambiar, luego tienes que cambiar el "listener"
del evento del click y removerlo. Hacer todo esto
es bastante complicado.
Esto también era una masiva fuente de "bugs" dentro del código
de Facebook.
Entonces dije: "ok, tienes razón, esto es probablemente una
de las cosas más difíciles.".
El contestó: "tengo una solución para esto".
Pensé: este tipo esta loco, esto jamás va a funcionar.
Nunca va a tener un buen desempeño. La reunión terminó
y por algunas semanas me olvidé de la idea.
Pero un fin de semana pensé: ok, tal vez debería probar esto,
tal vez haya algo aquí.
Antes de unirme a Facebook, trabajé en en una forma de encontrar
tus gremios en "World of Warcraft", y básicamente
necesitábamos buscar entre 20, 000 gremios.
Trabajé en muchas cosas de "performance"
para que desplegara resultados lo más rápido posible
cuando cambiabas los filtros en tiempo real.
Y pensé: ok, he pasado meses, tiempo completo, trabajando en
que esto tuviera un gran desempeño
intentémoslo con React. En la práctica, me tomó cerca de
media hora escribirlo,
y en realidad no tenía un buen desempeño, pero tenía
un desempeño similar.
Yo estaba impresionado, y hasta este día soy el fan más grande
de React en el mundo.
Yo estaba en el equipo de fotos y pasaba todo el tiempo
de mis horas de trabajo intentando usar React
en mis proyectos de mi equipo, evangelizando.
Sentía que podría cambiar al mundo,
lo cual ocurrió.
[Música]
[Chantastic] Jordan está logrando progreso en su proyecto.
Ha conseguido que otros se involucren y que
vean el valor que tiene. Pero no todos están impresionados.
Un manager empezó a notarlo, pero vió el proyecto
de Jordan como una distracción. Así que le pidió a
Lee Byron que se reuniera con Jordan
y le pusiera un alto para que enfocara los esfuerzos en Bolt.
Entramos a la sala. Al instante sabía
que esto iba a ser raro porque llegamos con diferentes energías.
Yo llegué como: ok Jordan, quiero entender como va tu proyecto,
pero también quiero
ayudarte a que nos aseguremos que estás inviertiendo nuestro
tiempo de la forma correcta y que estamos trabajando
en las cosas que van a tener longevidad y van a resolver los problemas
que tenemos. Y Jordan llegó con
"puedo mostarte una demo de lo que he estado trabajando", algo así
como "esto es muy emocionante,
y hace esto esto y esto otro". Y eventualmente,
al final de la reunión
tuve que admitir que tenía algo muy interesante entre manos.
Ahora estaba muy interesado en aprender más de lo que estaba haciendo.
Así que la presentación de Jordan fue para mí
algo así como:
Solo quiero invertir mi tiempo en esto y trabajarlo
si va a ser algo que las personas van a usar,
y si ese no es el caso, entonces no lo hagamos.
Pero opino que todas las formas en las que hemos
desarrollado interfaces de usuario hasta ahora
han tenido defectos. O son una biblioteca de JavaScript
que no cubre nuestras necesidades,
o es un modelo probado de hace 30 años para el desarrollo
de aplicaciones con interfaces de usuario.
Todos ellos sufren del mismo problema de raíz: el manejo del estado.
Y creo que esto es el camino hacia adelante.
y Lee, si pudieras indagar un poco más en el código
aprender más de ello y lo probarás, y entonces volvieras
para hablar de esto neuvamente, tal vez podríamos encontrar
una solución a esto. Y pensé: está bien, está bien.
Así que comencé a explorar el código y
era algo difícil de entender,
pero eventualmente pude jugar con el y
construir algunas cosas, y tuve que admitir
que había algo realmente interesante ahí. Y así fue
como me metí de lleno en el proyecto, y terminé
trabajando en el bastante tiempo en los siguientes
meses. Lee trajo esta meticulosa mentalidad de diseño
a estas cosas que ayudaron
bastante en las versiones iniciales de React en cuestión
de estándarizarlo y convertirlo
de algo así como un bebé feo que había crecido en Facebook
a algo que cualquier persona podía entender.
Había algunos problemas que me topé de inmediato
intentando entender el código para construir algo.
No eran solamente las herramientas y la cuestión
de que el modelo mental era muy diferente
de lo que estaba acostumbrado como ingeniero de UI.
No solo sintaxis y los conceptos de programación,
también la terminología era muy diferente.
Mis conclusiones eran: ok, toda la apuesta
gira en torno a que esto es más simple, pero
no puedo evitar sentir que esto es realmente complicado.
Sobretodo, deseaba poder entender el modelo
pero también esperaba
que esto de alguna forma terminara resolviendo algunas cosas.
Quería construir un glosario.
Qué son todas estás cosas, los conceptos y
todas las acciones o verbos
que están ocurriendo aquí. Así que literamente
lo listé todo. Y entonces iba con Jordan,
iba con otras personas trabajando en el proyecto,
y les preguntaba:
Entendí esto bien? Estás definiciones están correctas?
Y ellos contestaban: sí, o no, debes verlo de esta otra forma.
Y conversábamos una y otra vez y yo iba ajustando estas definiciones,
y mientras tanto nos dábamos cuenta
de que varios conceptos eran lo mismo,
mejor vamos a nombrarlos de una sola forma en lugar de ser dos cosas.
Así que desenmarañar todo esto y prácticamente escribirlo
terminó siendo como reimaginar el ciclo de vida
del componente, algo así
como todo la API pública de React.
Y yo estaba muy feliz todo el entusiasmo
alrededor de eso. Jordan decía: esto es increíble, esto
aclara todas las ideas.
A ese punto, varios compañeros también
comenzaron a ser parte del proyecto,
y pasé poco más del siguiente mes,
poniendo todo en orden
y cambiando considerablemente
la superficie de la API de React en el proceso.
Creo que fue fue el primer cambio, de ser esta cosa
que existia solamente en la mente de Jordan
y con la que otras personas jugaban, a algo del que,
de un día a otro, todo un equipo eramos responsables.
Donde la palabra "equipo" es algo así como muchos ingenieros
de interfaces de usuario repartidos por todo Facebook
que estabamos metidos de lleno en esta visión, y del que ahora
todos ahora podíamos usar la misma terminología
cada vez que alguien tenía una pregunta.
Ahora todos podíamos intentar responder una pregunta
más allá de Jordan. Ese fue el primer gran cambio.
Uno de los primeros proyectos donde React fue usado fue para UFI:
Universal Feedback Interface (Interfaz de Retroalimentación Universal)
que básicamente son los "me gusta", los comentarios y
la opción de compartir en la parte baja de cada publicación.
Esto fue todavía durante la era web de Facebook, cuando Facebook
en la web era algo así como
el mayor direccionador de "engagement".
El "Newsfeed" (Muro en Facebook en español) tenía mil millones de usuarios
al día, y estaba perfeccionado para tener gran desempeño.
Es una superficie altamente interactiva, donde
das click para dar un "me gusta", escribes para agregar comentarios,
y a la par queremos que los comentarios lleguen en vivo,
de manera que si le estas poniendo atención
mientras un comentario llega
queremos que aparezca justo ahí.
Y había este deseo en el producto
para que esa interfaz se sintiera como si fuera un chat,
y eso sonaban genial para la época.
Así que mientras eso comenzaba a funcionar, para el segundo
punto dijimos: si esto puede funcionar para este caso único
de mensajería, que tal si pudiera funcionar
para un caso completo de chats.
Esto era un área muy complicada y frágil, propensa a "bugs".
Eso fue cuando muchas de las ideas
en React cuadraron, la sintaxis de JSX fue introducida
y algunas de las ideas acerca de como trabajar con datos
y React ya estaban claros.
Algunos de nuestros ingenieros
junto al equipo de mensajería, representados por
Jing Chen si recuerdo bien,
se dieron cuenta de que necesitabamos una forma
diferente para pensar en el estado.
Mi nombre es Jing, y soy software engineer en
la infraestructura del producto en Facebook.
Flux es una arquitectura diseñada alrededor del
principio de React del flujo de datos unidireccional.
Junto con Flux, React podía ir más allá de la capa de la vista
para modelar toda una aplicación entera.
This shift in how to think about state paired
very well with how React was thinking about
updating UI and ended up being sort of the
next chapter for how to think about React
being more than just how do you model complicated
UI but how do you model sufficiently complicated
applications. Like this was something that
expanded the full screen and multiple touch
points and had navigation to it and it allowed
us to step into that next chapter. I remember
asking Jing like hey how's it going with this
React stuff? Do you think this is going to
work? She was like, yeah this is pretty good,
I'm pretty sure it's gonna work. That was
when I became more convinced.
[Music]
Instagram joined Facebook in 2012. I think
we had started calling it React by then and
there was a couple of engineers from Facebook
that went to join Instagram to help them expand
the product offering. At the time Instagram
was just an iOS and an Android app and they
wanted to have a web presence as well.
I spent 11 years in San Francisco, it was
really fun and I made a lot of great friends
but the the change of pace out in the in the
countryside is great. It's just very peaceful
and nice. I went to Facebook straight out
of school. I studied computer science undergrad
and I got a master's degree. Facebook was,
believe it or not, the cool place to work
back in 2010. It was this great product, that
everybody used. It was super cool on college
campuses and I was really excited to work
there.
I joined Facebook video. The pitch was, we're
the third largest video site in the world,
after YouTube and Dailymotion I think, and
there was like one engineer working on it
and like you get to be engineer number two
and I was like that sounds pretty cool. We
worked really closely with the iOS photos
team in the Android Photos team and we were
building an Instagram killer and nobody remembers
this but it was called Facebook Camera. One
morning the photo's team got called into the
office early. They said like be at HQ at 8am
and then the VP of engineering was like hey
we bought Instagram, they're your new co-workers
now. And these were like the people that were
like our fierce competitors you know. We looked
at them a little bit as the enemy, I'm sure
they looked at us a little bit as the enemy.
They were a really small team at the time,
they had their core fundamentals really nailed
but there was a lot of stuff they needed to
figure out, that they did not have the team
to figure out on their own and a big one of
those was what does it mean for Instagram
to be on the web. The web experience is really
important for driving growth and so this was
a pretty important priority and so me and
this designer, Maykel Loomans, started building
all the web stuff. And that's kind of where
React enters the picture, when we started
developing this website. [Music]
We were given this mandate to use client rendering
so I went to the product infrastructure team
at Facebook, which was run by Tom Occhino.
Product infrastructure's role was to support
any team that needed help and do it in a way
that your key indicators of success are going
to be other teams saying "yeah that really
helped us". You go to them and you kind of
consult the Council of Elders and they give
you their recommendation and I said, hey we
need to do client rendering, what do we do?
And the recommendation at the time was yeah
we don't know. We've got like three different
things that we're working on, you should go
try one. We had something called Bolt.js,
there was a second thing called JS.HTML and
then there was this this thing called React.
Pete went and spoke to Jordan about using
React and he came and talked to me about potentially
using Bolt for it but I think he really, really
liked Jordan's ideas around functional programming.
The conceptual model of react was like crazy
Innovative and it really, really spoke to
me. My background was in distributed systems.
I was not somebody that loved front-end or
thought front-end was doing things well, so
the fact that React came in with like a totally
fresh approach and didn't really care too
much about existing best practices, like I
was I was on board with that. So while I had
evaluated all three I really just dove in
on React to build a prototype first and that
ended up shipping on Instagram.com which was
the second use of React in production ever
and the first use of building a full application
end to end in React.
When I chose React for Instagram it was not
well known within Facebook and it was this
kind of crazy science experiment.
Not even close. By the time Instagram was,
and you know Pete started playing with it,
it was significantly better than it was in
the early, early stage but it still needed
a ton of iteration. We had to take this thing
that was very much tied to Facebook's infrastructure
which back then was a big giant PHP application
and I had to go get that working in a Django
application which is a totally different system.
And what was key was not doing that once but
making that a repeatable process and making
sure that that pipeline didn't break. I think
he hit a number of really interesting problems
along the way which quite proved the fact
that React was not quite ready for that scale
and along the way Pete, and the team that
he was working with, built a lot of really
interesting things. [Music]
Some of these products ended up being fairly
successful. There were relatively short time
to deliver a relatively high quality product.
That showed that this model could work and
it was not just that, but people liked developing
using it. And so that kind of spread and took
off and especially is it got more and more
investment, it became clear that this was
what we wanted to use and it was really ads
that was kind of using Bolt more. It had a
higher level of investment, more people working
in that code base, that already knew it and
more components so it was a harder shift to
make.
The ads team just before I joined ads from
the mobile team had done a full rewrite of
the ads creation flow into Bolt. Which took
them I think upwards of six months replacing
a very old PHP application with what time
was considered a very modern JavaScript application.
But at the same time React was also now actually
deployed for real on Facebook and had a team
that was forming around it. So we now had
two viable frameworks that were both live
on Facebook, both solving real problems. We
shouldn't have two. Especially two that were
similar. Similar enough to confuse people.
Like if you looked at the code, their code
almost looked identical but that worked really
differently. It would actually be an absolute
nightmare if you had to work in both. So we
had to decide which to use.
[Music]
A lot of this ended up being a conversation
between myself and Jordan. We did an evaluation
of both of them. A lot of performance-based
stuff and trying to figure out where the edge
cases were. On the pro side of React, obviously
there's all the things that we know now: it
handles complexity way, way more. Even when
writing the ads creation flow in Bolt we had
already hit one place that you just could
not do in Bolt without writing spaghetti code,
and you can do in React. So we knew in the
future even if it was only 10% of the experience
we were building, we're going to run into
this problem again. Now it might only be 10%
unmaintainable but as you scale that across
a company that is growing rapidly, this becomes
an absolute mess. The cons of it on the other
hand were that React in a lot of ways was
not battle tested yet. There's a lot of things
that simply didn't work in React. It couldn't
handle forms, they'd never done a text box
and there's a lot of complexities around handing
awkward form controls like radio buttons and
so on that it messed up. Just performance
issues where it would try and re-render large
blocks so they hadn't had to do all of the
performance improvements that obviously exist
now. On the organizational side the other
con was that we had just done the six-month
rewrite in Bolt. Facebook had done an IPO
recently and the stock had halved since IPO.
Facebook wasn't making enough money and so
the ads team is the team that makes, you know,
that's where the money starts. If we stop
for four months we're gonna have to tell everybody
sorry no money for you so there was a lot
of conversation back and forth about all this.
It got very difficult. Initially a lot of
the engineers that used Bolt, including Shane,
realized just what you said. Like look we've
invested so much in this thing and it's really
worked for all this stuff, certainly we can
work through the next set of challenges we're
having. So initially there was opposition
to React coming in and saying like how are
you gonna, you know, this new thing that's
not even proven yet. This is our business,
this is really important. When Jordan and
I were working through it, there was definitely
uh some emotions uh there um and mostly I
think it came from uh each of us having a
lack of context of where the other one was
coming from. So I think there was a lot of
talking past each other. In the end Mike Schroepfer
stepped in and said, look make the right technical
decision, make the right long-term decision
and whatever it is I'll back you up. But if
you need to pause product development for
four months you can. We all kind of just got
in rooms and you know worked through all these
things and got everything out in the air of
what's a technical problem, what's an organization
problem, what's a financial problem and kind
of a came to the understanding eventually
through uh with lots and lots of coffee that
React was the right way to go, but um it was
not a straight line at all. He ultimately
was one of the biggest proponents or decision
makers in ads switching everything over to
React and that doesn't happen in most companies.
In most companies if that's your baby project
you try to undermine the other, the upstart,
because you're you know you're really defensive
over your own thing. That was not the vibe
at Facebook at the time and I think that Shane
in particular really exemplified that. There
was still a lot of work to do on the ads creation
flow. Tensions were mounting and the team
was stuck. Here again to get them unstuck,
is Jing Chen. We'd have this thorny management
issue and a lot of people disagreeing with
each othe,r up and down the management chain
on both sides of you know in ads and in this
product infrastructure group those building
react and we'd send Jing in to talk to the
engineers and everyone would come out, like
patting each other on the back, full agreement,
a plan to move forward. So she's great at
building a consensus because she's able to
drill into the important technical details,
identify them really quickly and get everyone
talking about the same thing. She obviously
helped both build the product but she also
made sure that every time we found a bug in
React or just something that it didn't handle
yet, she either stepped back from product
and then just fixed the framework. Or she
went back to the team and said look we need
two or three engineers working on this stuff
for the next month to unblock the ads team.
The ads manager was complicated enough that
it actually ended up being a really great
source of performance improvements and finding
like, where are the true points where it just
doesn't quite scale. So I think it was a lot
of using the building blocks that we had and
as you start to assemble them into a really
complicated looking application, what are
the new problems that come out of that, that
we need to solve. And there was definitely
a lot of those. This is one of the most fun
intense periods of my career as I remember
it. We would be going to meet with the team
and we would have to help them put some feature
in and we would code it up ourselves first
in React just to make sure that the that they
wouldn't hit any rough edges. Or more like
to find all the rough edges that we knew they'd
hit and figure out what the solutions would
be. So it was really exciting because we were
working on two things at the same time. One
was delivering this really complicated, really
important software project for Facebook: the
ads manager. And the other was refining this
framework that we really believed in which
was React. By the time we had rebuilt the
ads creation flow, which I think took about
four months, it had been battle tested with
basically everything about the browser supports,
all the form fields and everything, and also
massive performance issues that had been resolved,
so at that point it was kind of felt that
it was ready to be open source because you
know we we used it in multiple different types
of contexts and that you know it would actually
be generally useful to the public. [Music]
[Mumbled question]
What did you say, Evan?
Uh there is not, sorry. Open sourcing React
was never a question for me. That was the
goal from the very beginning. Tom had this
idea, he called it project perception, and
he was really angry I think it's probably
the best word for it. He was angry that Facebook
was hiring all these luminaries from the JavaScript
world. They would come to Facebook and you
know because we discouraged people from writing
client-side JavaScript and because it was
a hard environment to maneuver in, they would
actually go pick up mobile because that was
where a lot of the interesting client-side
development was happening. And Tom was determined
to change this around. I remember going to
this conference and I was talking to someone
and I told them I worked at Facebook on JavaScript
and they're like why would you do that? I
hate what Facebook does to the JavaScript
industry. You have hired all these really
great people from these really great projects
and we have no idea what they're working on
now. They've given nothing back. So I think
when React came along I started very early
on talking about if this thing works for us
I really want us to find a path to open source.
And I was running that up the management chain
very early so when the time came to open source
it, there were some meetings, it was controversial
but we had all the support we needed already.
The process of open sourcing is interesting.
There's first a technical problem to solve.
You have to figure out how to extract it out
of your infrastructure and make it work in
the open source, which is all the homework
that we did for Instagram. We made this call
that like we will not impact developer productivity
at all, it's going to be entirely on the open
source team, which was just a bunch of people
that wanted to open source it, to make it
work. Then actually pulling the trigger on
open source, we had to write a lot of documentation.
We spent actually a lot of time with the documentation
to explain like, hey what is React, what are
all the concepts and we tried to put ourselves
in the shoes of somebody that want to build
an app. How do we give the documentation in
a way it helps them do that. Paul O'Shannessy
did a lot of this because he really had the
experience with what the ecosystem needed
to make this work at the time. Paul O'Shannessy
was a huge force on open sourcing. As was
James Pearce who was the head of Facebook
open source. James had joined the company
and he really wanted to change Facebook's
open source image. We had previously open
sourced a lot of stuff but we let it rot.
We would say, hey we're an open source company,
here's our great framework and then we would
just never maintain it. And James and Paul
in particular were pretty instrumental in
saying, hey if we're going to open source
React, we're going to do it right. Internally
there was a lot of excitement because we had
already been using this thing for a while
and it was working for us, we were excited
about it. We chose JSconf US which was kind
of the, I don't know, the Oscars of JavaScript
- is that fair representation maybe? You know
all the celebrities are there and everyone's
paying attention and everybody watches it
live on YouTube. Tom and Jordan put together
this presentation. Tom is a great speaker
and Jordan is a brilliant engineer, it was
like a Lennon and McCartney type of situation.
There was no way that this thing could possibly
fail.
[Music] It was in Florida, at like 9 00 a.m.
We were in Menlo Park and we woke up early,
we took the first bus into the office. It
was completely empty and we're getting ready
to like press the button on the repo to open
source it. Jordan and I were all excited we
got up on stage. I'm going to talk a bit about
how we do JavaScript application development
at Facebook. It was a little unconventional,
I did a little bit of it, he did more of it.
So along with react we are shipping an embeddable
XML syntax and we're calling that JSX. And
we jumped into showing some code and that
code looked different, it looked weird. Here
we have React used with JSX. And people were
rightfully skeptical we'll call it. Everyone
hated it, everyone thought it was awful!
[Música]
Internamente estabamos esperando una mejor recepción.
O al menos un "oh, eso suena interesante"
Pensamos que habría algunos nerds de algún
lenguaje de programación que pensarían
"oh, podría hacer programación funcional en la UI,
al menos eso es interesante".
Fue una lección de humildad, fue una decepción para nosotros
porque trabajamos varias noches
y fines de semana para tener esto listo para ser open source,
y entonces cuando lo lanzamos, todos lo odiaron.
El detalle en donde todos se enfocaron fue que las personas
realmente odiaron JSX.
No he visto este video hace tiempo.
Estos divs no son exactamente a lo que estas acostumbrado.
No son nodos del DOM.
Son especialmente reactions, y te diré porque eso es importante.
No recuerdo haber pensado en que lo odiarían.
No recuerdo en lo en lo absoluto haber pensado que tuitearían
tantas cosas acerca de eso.
Esta es la diapositiva. Aún no habíamos hablado
de los problemas que intentábamos solucionar.
Tampoco habíamos hablado de porque esto funcionaba
para nosotros, o cuales eran los principios de diseño.